yo what's up y'all today we've got
something a little bit different than
our normal scheduled programming uh I'm
going to take a mini episode today to
talk about how to generate endless
attack vectors on a given web
application um I think this is something
that we all sort of run into when we're
attempting to hack a web application is
you push you push you push and then
you're just out of attack vectors um and
over the years I've put together uh a
couple tips and framework of sorts um in
order to help me get past those sort of
plateaus that I reach when auditing an
application so I thought I'd take some
time to share those with you
[Music]
today before we get into my content I
want to do a shout out um to a piece of
content that I think is one of the
finest pieces on this topic and that is
uh the naham con 2023 talk by Douglas
day aka the Archangel um and he talks
about in that in that um in that video
he talks about this concepts of nose
within an application and how um a lot
of the vones that he finds comes from
his knowledge of the application and how
he uh walks through the app and looks
for NOS or things that he shouldn't be
allowed to do um and so I'm not going to
try to go over that and uh reiterate
everything that he says in there
definitely go just Google naham con um
Douglas day or the arch angel um and put
that into uh put that into YouTube and
watch that video excellent content there
um and definitely keep an eye out for
that concept of nose when you're
searching when you're reading through
the application um look for things that
you shouldn't be able to do and give
that a shot he also does a shout out a
little bit in that in that um YouTube
video to this whole concept of rback
matrixing so um role-based Access
Control matrixing
matrixing creating a matrix uh about uh
the RO back based access controls on a
specific site um and I think that's a
really insightful piece uh of the talk
as well um and really speaks to the
thoroughness that Douglas takes and
brings into any web application
assessments that he does and I've worked
with Douglas many times on live hacking
events and I've seen firsthand the crazy
attack fures that he comes up with just
by thoroughly thoroughly understanding
the application getting it configured
into all of its different states um so
definitely an expert on the topic uh so
definitely check out that video we'll
link it down in the description below um
okay so uh on from from Douglas's tips
uh to mine I've got let's see six
different sections here that I want to
talk about and the first one is kind of
similar to what um Douglas was talking
about but I have this written down use
the application like a human not like a
hacker okay so often times when I go
into an application I'm thinking all
right how do I hack this how do I hack
this how do I hack this and that makes
sense because that's our goal in the
scenario right is to be able to hack the
application but I think sometimes that
is inversely helpful it's it's unhelpful
for us to actually understand what the
application's about what data is being
used in the application what is
important what processes are important
um and so uh when I when I remind myself
to use the application like a human um
what essentially what I do is I leave
burp or kaido or on or whatever I'm
proing just to keep all that traffic but
I don't use any of it and I just step
through the application the UI like a
human I'm trying to figure out exactly
what that application is supposed to be
used for what sort of user Journeys the
user would go on as they're going
through that application and trying to
get the application into a little bit
more of a configured State I ran into an
example the other day of this uh concept
resulting in a bug when I was working on
a website um that essentially allowed
you to configure specific devices and so
I selected one of the devices from the
drop down and then it gave you a bunch
of like options you could select and I
did this for a couple of the the devices
but none of the options seemed really
interesting um and then I was like okay
well you know let me be a little bit
more thorough with my testing go went
back kind of clicked through um the
various different types of of um of
devices that I could configure and I
found uh a a device further down the
list that allowed me to configure some
special settings and the settings
resulted in a full read ssrf um and so
definitely make sure you're you're one
being thorough in your testing and
exhausting all the user journey and code
paths um and also using the application
like like a human not like a hacker I
don't know maybe that doesn't make a
bunch of sense but it kind of rings in
my in my head um all right next uh
reading the documentation and looking
for canot statements okay this is so
underrated it's ridiculous like and it
and it's not sexy so I understand why
most people don't do it but um going in
just literally dumping the whole
documentation for a product and reading
it all like literally sometimes during
live hacking events when I'm like brain
Fred and I can't be at my computer
anymore I'll take the documentation for
a product export it to a PDF or or get
it in some sort of form that I can get
it on my e-reader and I'll just take my
e-reader out to a hammock and just like
Leisure read through the documentation
okay and when you're doing that you're
looking for a couple specific things
you're looking for cannot statements so
xuser cannot do XYZ um you're you're
looking for uh boundaries that have been
set up in in the application um which
we'll talk a little bit more uh about
later um and like Douglas mentioned
before you're looking for those NOS
you're looking for anything that says um
you know the limit on this is X right
because that's something that we could
potentially bypass and it always helps
when you're writing a report to to be
able to reference a specific line of
documentation uh because if you can do
that it's very hard to debate that it's
an issue because um then you can start
talking to the program about this whole
concept excuse me this whole concept of
user trust where you've built
documentation for your product the user
you the user trusts you that this
documentation is accurate and then you
violated that trust by um creating a
product that does not actually comply
with the standards that you've set up
for this user so makes for a very
convincing argument in the context of a
report and I've never gotten well I
can't say never sometimes they'll just
say like yeah that's a documentation bug
it shouldn't it shouldn't be there but
most of the time in their own
documentation they will they will pay
out the Bounty um for if you have a
piece of documentation that contradicts
what the application's actual
functionality is um so definitely check
that out um in addition to reading
documentation uh not only the help
documentation but go and read the forums
go and read the help desk facts go and
read the GitHub issues go and read the
wikis right um just a couple live
hacking events back I found a bug um in
in a piece of software very widely used
piece of software and the way I found
that was going to a GitHub issue and I
found an issue where I I I found a a um
yeah an issue on issues uh that said hey
you know there's this specific
functionality that happens every once in
a while that kind of sort sort of looks
like a security bug but it's just a bug
and and they're like okay we'll fix it
and so I looked into how that happened
and I found a way to forcibly recreate
it um and force that bug to happen to
other users resulted in a great bug and
actually won me the most impactful um
bug on a specific Target in the Life
hacking at um so definitely don't skip
those GitHub issues always search for
things like security or um any keywords
that might be correlated to that
specific products like disclosure or or
um leak or anything like that um and
read all the GitHub issues you can get
your hands on to understand why that
product is acting the way that it is in
some some weird
scenarios okay um next was look at the
grade out areas in the application now
this is pretty standard but um in an
application often times there will be
buttons that are disabled and and um
text areas you're not supposed to be
able to modify fire right in and we all
know that once you know you submit the
form or whatever you can just add you
know you can intercept it at that level
right and uh and modify text boxes that
shouldn't be modifiable and stuff like
that and and sometimes that does result
in vulnerabilities and is certainly
something to be thinking about when
you're coming up with attack factors um
but I found that modifying things at the
UI level allows you to use the
application more like a human right and
understand the flow that um the
application goes through which may give
you additional insight into request
formatting and stuff like that so you
don't have to like fight with the format
from minifi JS file or something of the
like um so that's that's a cool way to
do it um there's lots of ways you can do
it uh you can use uh like a burp match
and replace or kaido match and replace
to um you know remove disabled elements
I personally have a um uh JavaScript
bookmark liet that I've been using in my
browser for a very long time uh that
will just go through and find every
disabled element and undisable it um
which is really helpful and uh it also
takes hidden elements and unhides them
which is also helpful um so maybe you
can code up that uh bookmarklet similar
or I'm sure there's better ways of doing
it through like a Chrome extension or
something of the like um and I'm sure
someone in the community will come up
with a better solution than my hacky
little bookmarklet um so keep that
technique in mind as well paying
attention to those grade out areas of
the application re-enabling those and
then walking through the code path
um in the UI so that you understand how
everything how the application flows and
maybe you can skip steps or something of
the like okay next one is look for
information that is in the UI or excuse
me that is not in the UI but is in the
API response okay so this can be
indicative of a couple things uh it can
be indicative of the uh API being used
in other areas of the application and
they just you know bundle all that data
together um it could be indicative of
Legacy uh features that are still there
right so if you had a feature that uses
a piece of information before and
they've removed that feature um pay
attention to what information is being
returned in that API recall or that API
response because uh it will lead you to
understanding uh what that application
functionality was in the past and you
might even be able to look up like um JS
files on web archive or something of the
like uh to be able to figure out why
that functionality was there um or it
can also just kind of inform your gut
and allow you to make a more educated
guess on maybe fields that you could
modify in other places of the
application or even
um uh even like if the application has
like a start out area of like text and
but that text is in the API response
sometimes programs will accept bugs like
that because they're trying to prevent
uh that leak even if someone does get
access to that person's account so
that's another that's another cool tip
there is if you have particularly grade
out or censored information maybe the
social security number only has the last
four digits or maybe your email is only
being shown the first character and then
the at whatever.com um if you can find a
way to leak that then that can violate
the security boundaries in the threat
model that that application has set up
and those are intentional security
decisions that are being made by the
team so um something to keep in mind
there as well this doesn't always result
in a bug just mind you and um one of the
quotes that I really loved from
Douglas's talk that I mentioned earlier
was make sure you evaluate the security
impact of your nose because sometimes
there is no no security impact but um in
scenarios like I mentioned before where
there's an intentional security decision
made to conceal a certain piece of
information if you can link that
information it might be of something of
interest to the team and we know that uh
unlike Joel or unlike some of the other
hackers we have on this podcast I a big
um fan of submitting every bug that's a
vulnerability getting that money whether
it's a low or medium or a crit or High
um so don't let that deter you let's get
submitting those bugs anyway um yeah and
and so the next one that I had on the
list here was look between uh look for
differences between in the UI between
two different accounts okay so if you've
got a admin account and a non-admin
account or you've got different tiers of
um our back Ro based access controls
make sure you're looking at the
differences in the UI as well and that
can tell you and inform you which area
of the application you should try to
attack as the less privileged user this
also goes for um for uh applications
that have different
like user tiers I guess that are not
really accessible to the normal user for
example if you have like a support agent
or a staff um account try to figure out
what is informing the client side that
that user um or that support agent or
staff account is is a staff account and
then try to replicate that on your
account because then you may be able to
walk through so much of the application
on the client side much easier rather
than having to dig through JS files and
break your brain trying to read minified
JavaScript okay last one that I had here
on the list was pay walls um anytime
there's a pay wall we talk about this
all the time um on the podcast anytime
there's a pay wall just pay it just just
just pay the pay bypass the pay wall
with one account and by paying it right
and then have the other account and try
to access some of those same features
it's so often that I see you know people
say oh this feature is only available in
the premium but that's just a function
of something that they've Exposed on the
on the on the UI and I I imagine that
this is a part of sort of a flawed
development cycle right um that they're
developing this whole product and then
they're saying okay well where do we
want to put these tiers in and all let's
put the tear here here here here right
and they kind of tweak that over time
right um but a lot of that stuff is just
happening in the front end uh and it's
not being implemented on the back end as
well after the functionalities already
been developed okay so as a as a as a
review we talked about checking out that
awesome talk by Douglas day um on nose
and and how to you know search for nose
within an application to come up with
great attack vectors um using the
application like a human not like a
hacker try to figure out how the app
works what makes sense in the
application um uh from a user's
perspective Ive and literally just don't
even look at your your HTTP proy just
use the application and get it into
weird configured States right um read
the documentation and not only the
documentation read forms read GitHub
issues read help Des stuff read wikis
read all that and assimilate it all
and try to understand the far-reaching
breadth of this application understand
the deepest depths of this application
you have to get intimate with the
application in these scenarios um so
make sure you're reading everything
about it right um look for grade out
areas in the application and try to use
those to indicate um where some of the
security boundaries might be um and this
is also a great indicator uh in a report
like hey no this button is specifically
disabled and I am able to utilize it
it's very hard to hard to debate with
that in the context of a
report um look for information that is
not in the UI but is in the API response
that can inform where old Legacy
features might have be been or what kind
of information is getting stored in
different objects which can lead to
other
vulnerabilities um look for the
differences in the UI between two
different accounts of different tier uh
tier level um so this could be sort of
an rback situation or it could be like a
like a more vertical um privilege
escalation to like staff user or
something of the like which you can
emulate via match and replace on the
client side once you've identified how
the client side is is identifying those
users and then finally pay walls make
sure you're you're not shying away from
that 20 $30 investment to get a two or
3K Buck all right that's it for today
hope you all got something out of that
um let me know if I missed anything
shoot me a message on Twitter or uh on
the info criticalthinking podcast. if
you've got any more cool attack Vector
um
thinking attack Vector formulation tips
that you'd like to share all right see
youall next week
[Music]
ch